congratulations, you've made it
through exam one, you've gone
through the vegetable portion of
the course, the ER diagram and the
normalization, the DDL, DML, and
now we're ready to write SQL code
based on the diagrams that we've
created earlier in the course.
Just as a reminder, about 85% of
all technology positions require SQL
Server, so this particular class,
5300, is a great opportunity to develop
foundation skills, and if you have
an interest in developing a more
depth in the area to kind of carve
out SQL as one of your core areas,
we also invite you to consider taking
the advanced course, data 5310.
All right. The deliverables for
today, we have a blue triad. As a
reminder from the syllabus, blue
triad, in this particular case, we'd
like you to log in to SQL Server
to load the planet dataset. Planet
data set is located under files
in Canvas and we have instructions
elsewhere on how to log in to SQL
Server, how to load data files. So
once you get the planet data set
loaded, you'll be ready for today.
Speaking of planets, I love
anything to deal with space.
And years ago, I wrote a proposal
for an honors class using SQL Server
and astronomy data. We thought it
would be great to go and use the
telescope. and anyways it didn't work
out and I think the project went to
studying snails or some other thing
it was a long time ago but we still
have this initial data set that was
put together as as just a proof of
concept the blue triad for today
you'll follow along as I go through
different coding examples and then we
also have the blue triad so once you
follow along we have some specific
blue triads you'll upload your notes
along with screen captures or whatever
you take to show that you were
fully paying attention to the video
today to help you prepare for the
labs and for the exam. We also have
a group by animation separate from
this video, and there is a group by
animation quiz associated with that.
And then for those on campus,
Thursday you will have lab two, and
for those of you online, the second
part of the week you'll have lab
two where you'll be able to
demonstrate your skills in SQL Server.
Anyways, let's ahead and get started.
I was trying to take a picture
of this helicopter when some car
drove in front of me and then I
noticed it did have kind of an
interesting tail light that stood out
to me, but just trying to catch a
picture of this helicopter here.
All right, we'll start with the
most basic SQL, select statement,
from statement, where statement,
I'll describe that, and then we'll
move into aggregate functions,
group by, and having, which is
arguably the more a difficult part
of single table queries that we're
covering today. The problem that
I've noticed over the last forever
years is if I cover all of the
basics in SQL Server in a traditional
class, by the time we get to a
group by having, it's almost the
end of class, everybody's tired
and they're ready to go. And then
we cover the most important topic
in the last five or six minutes.
So we're going to flip that and
cover those a little bit earlier.
So let's go ahead and move over
to our Playground in SQL Server.
In SQL Server, you can use
a couple of items to comment
in the code. If I use dash
dash, you'll notice that
everything turns green, and
I can indicate select from
and where, and that code won't run
when I eventually execute and run
this code. I can always click on
a new query. That will give me a
new tab, and then it's good to
make comments just to keep track of
what you're actually doing to create
documentation for those that go
ahead of you. You can also use a
forward slash and then an asterisk.
You'll notice it turns green,
and then you can include comments
here, and then to finish it
off, I just remember that the
asterisks go together with the
text, and so in this case you
could use asterisks and then
the forward slash and that will
finish the comment. So this
could work with multiple lines
until you indicate. Either way,
whichever works better for you.
But in terms of the most simple code
you can write, we'll learn about
or we'll use this more often later,
but SQL does work with literal
values and it also works with
column values or attributes, and you
can use combinations of the two,
I could put select 5 plus 2, and
in this particular case, there's
no table, there's no from clause
needed. I can run this and it simply
adds this information together,
5 plus 2, and we'll come back
to order of operation a little
bit later as well. But typically,
we'll use a table or tables.
Today we're using a single
table, and we'll indicate select
everything at this point from
the planet table. And then if I
highlight it, I can run that
particular code, and this gives
us a starting point to work on
the planet data set. Now, we'll
cover one more keyword, and
that would be the where clause.
The SELECT statement indicates
which column or columns you're
interested in using, and right now
we're using the SELECT statement.
Typically you don't want to
use SELECT, and you can read
in the Ben-Gon book about
why in detail, but just as
an example, if somebody
comes in and deletes columns,
the SELECT statement will
still work, and maybe you don't
want it to work. Or if somebody
adds columns, you may not
know which columns were added.
So one of the problems with
the SELECT star is that you
lose a little bit of control
over what is changed or what
hasn't changed in the dataset.
And so for class, you're just fine
using select star to represent
all columns just for the
sake of convenience. But in a
traditional business, you normally
wouldn't include a select star
just to be more descriptive. And
we will discuss that in detail
throughout the semester as well.
The from statement is which
table or tables. In our case, we
only have one table called planet.
And then the where statement
is considered predicate logic.
And predicate logic is based on
relational algebra, which is kind of
the foundations for SQL Server.
And the idea of predicate logic in
SQL Server, normally things are
either true or they're false. But in
SQL Server, they can be true, false,
or unknown. So we have a three
logic in SQL Server. True, false,
or unknown. and this is where I
could refer to a column, for instance,
where mass is greater than 50.
And the predicate logic
here will evaluate each one
of these rows and determine it
to be true, false, or unknown,
and we'll discuss null values
and unknown a little bit
later. In this case, we just
have true or false values,
and so it indicates all of these
four rows of data because they
have a mass of greater than 50. So
the idea of predicate logic is we
take a table and we remove out
rows that don't match the criteria
that we happen to be looking for.
That is the basis of select
from and where. And so
now let's take a look at
some aggregate functions.
I've mentioned the where clause
is the predicate logic. But now we
have some built-in aggregate
functions for SQL Server. In the data
5310 class, we will be using
user-defined functions where you
could create your own function based
on company formulas or algorithms.
But there are five basic aggregate
functions that are available
to you. And they're very straightforward
math, basic math. We have
the count function, which will
simply count the number of rows.
We have the minimum function,
determine the minimum value.
The maximum will determine
the maximum value, sum will
add up the columns that
you're interested in, and then
average will take the arithmetic,
the mean, the average mean
of the particular data
that you're looking
at. So let's switch over to SQL Server.
Okay,
let's add these aggregate functions.
So we have count, min, max, sum,
av. And these need to be
typed out as they are, so
you'd have to have avg and
not the full word average.
Let's take a look at one instance
of a null value using the
count function. If you take a
look at distance from the sun,
take a look at that particular column,
and you'll notice that
there is one null value.
So when you count, you generally
have two options. One, you would do
count, and then star, and that would
mean show me all of the columns,
and regardless of if they have null
values or not. So in this case,
you could see on the left-hand
side that there would be 10 rows.
And if you take a normal
column that has a value,
you would also get the
10 rows or a column that
is a primary key because
it can't be left null.
That's possible. However, if you do count
and you need this information,
you count it based
on distance from the sun,
you'll see that it goes from
10 to 9 now if we go on
to let's say is it moons
yeah so let's select the
moons for some of our other
aggregate functions and we
can have the list of moons
here and now if I put in
min and moons and I run this
it gives me a big old zero
which is a number right it's
not null but it does Let's
leave the column name blank.
And in this case, I want
to give it an alias.
And you can use the ads. If you
don't want to use the ads, that's
fine. So one of, to me, either of
those are best practice. I like to
use as just because it's a little
more descriptive. And then you would
give it the name. So min, moons,
and you can see where it says no
column name, and I run this, and
now it says there's the min, moons.
And of course, everything
in the select statement
is separated by commas,
and you determine the order
of your output columns by which order
you included in the select statement.
In this case, I'm starting
with moons, but then I could go
right to max and moons or
some other column as max moons
and run this information, and
we know that 67 is the max.
So we're getting more
information, descriptive
information by just using
these aggregate functions.
Now, we've already done count. We
could do sum. We want to sum the moons.
And this would be a sum
of the moons, 178 total
moons, just according
to my last data set. And
then, of course, the average
would give the average
number of moons, and that's the
mean average. Go ahead and pause
the video and try this with your
data set, the planet data set.
These are similar to the coding
questions that you'll get on
the exam and on the labs, and
so the blue triads will help
get you prepared for those labs
and for the exams. Write an
SQL statement that shows the
lowest and highest planet mass.
Include alias when appropriate, and
that would indicate that if it's
going to be no name for your column,
you'll want to give it an alias.
Okay, here is the code.
We have select min, mass,
the minimum is the aggregate
function, as min mass,
comma, maximum mass, as
maximum mass from the planet.
Perfect. Okay, now we're ready
for a research question. We asked
Dr. Sigurd, go through the planets
and tell us your interest in that
particular planet. She likes
astronomy too, so does Mark Dawson.
All right, so Mercury, low.
Venus, medium.
Earth, high.
So Dr. Sigurd has listed her interest,
low, medium, high on the planets.
If we just use the average moons,
as you know, it gives one result.
It just takes up one row.
But now we want to see
the average moons based
on Dr. Sigurd's interest.
And so if I come up to our
statement, and this is arguably
the first question that you're
asked on an interview, and
this is something that will
100% be on the exam in very
similar format, and I'll explain
the rule in just a minute.
So now we want to see the
interest and the average moons.
And we get an error message.
We know if we do average
moons, we get one value.
And if we do interest, we get 10
rows of output. We get 10 values.
So the question is, how do we fix this?
And long before AI, this was
mine as a kid, Bobby Mills, I
had Jack, Jack and the Beanstalk,
or Jack Bean Needle, but
this one, Jack, what has he
got to say here? He's saying,
oh,
we need a group buy.
Thank you, Jack.
What the heck?
Ah!
What's a group buy for?
Well, let's take a look.
And if we read this error
code, it does give a hint.
Let me get this error message,
maybe we need a group buy clause.
hmm so now we have to group by
here's the rule if we have an
aggregate function and then we
have a non-aggregate function
you must group by the non
-aggregate function in this case
we add our next keyword
we have select from where
group by and in this case
we have to say group by
interest, and if we have more
than one non-aggregate in
the select statement, we
would have to include it here.
And now I think the thing that's
most important at this stage is
how many rows do you expect to
show up by using this group by.
Now let's take a look at
our table, and we have
how many values in interest. We have low,
medium, and high. In this particular
case, it's going to provide
three groups, low, medium, and
high. And then what it's going to
do is take the average for just
the low group, for just the medium
group, or just a large group. So
the research question could say,
in terms of interest, does
Reagan tend to be interested in
planets that have lots of moons
or very few moons? And that
would, you know, effectively be
the research question. But before
we run it, I think it's important
to think about grouping.
I have a deck of cards, and
this particular deck just gives
some ideas of groups, and more
importantly, how many rows
you would expect. So for
instance, if we grouped by color,
the output you would expect to
have two rows, right? And it
would give you whatever we're
looking for, maximum, average,
min, sum, count, and so forth.
However, as you know, we
can also group by suit.
And so for instance, if this
was count and then group
by suit. For clubs, we
would have a value of two.
Spades, we'd have a value of one.
Hearts, we would have a value of
one, and diamonds. But more
importantly, how many rows do we expect
for the output? And you would expect
four rows of output. Give me the
average or min, max, whatever those
aggregate functions are. Now we
have the code set up. We run this.
We get three rows, high low and
medium we don't have a column name
so we could say as and then bridge
rows now you can either use a
quote or you can use the brackets
the brackets tend to always
work and where it becomes
really important is if you download
a data set and for instance
there was something called
interest moon column with a space
the only way you could run
this without fixing the data in
getting rid of that space would
be to put brackets around it.
So brackets tend to be very
powerful and it's just an option
for providing the alias as well
or you could use the quote.
And so we run this. Now we
have average rows per entrance,
high and low and medium.
And so based on this really
simple study, it looks like Dr.
Sigurd is interested in planets
that have lots of moons.
And now armed with that
extra group by, select
from where group by, here's another one.
Pause the screen, if you would,
and try this as another blue triad.
Again, at the end of the video, you'll
upload. If you just do the blue triads,
copy those images into a single
Word document. If you take
notes and want to include
that, but again, mainly looking
for just screen caps showing
that you followed along today.
So here's the correct code. We
have select location, locations and
non-aggregate, max density, aggregate
as max, min density, aggregate.
And then in this case, we
have to group by the location.
The halving clause, by definition,
the halving clause can be used to
restrict which groups are displayed.
Remember, if we had
grouped this by color,
in this case, we would have two
rows that show up. And that would
be using the group by clause.
Now the halving clause could
decide whether these groups stay
or go. So for instance, let's say
that in order to keep these
groups, you want them to have
at least three cards or you
don't want to have them at all.
And that would be having the count
of three or greater. And what
would happen if you did that is you
would get rid of this particular
group. Now, if you said they need
to have at least one in the
group, this has two and this has
three, and you run that having
clause, then both would be retained.
So in a way, you can get rid of
rows that you think are outliers
or you just don't want to
consider because you want to get
rid of those. So in this case,
we can use the having clause.
Here we have our problem.
Select location average moons
from planet. Group by location. We
have an aggregate, non-aggregate.
We have a whole animation on group
by. It's just because it's forgotten
so quickly that the need for
aggregate, non-aggregate has to
have a group by. And then if we just
run this information without the
having clause, here's an example.
we have zero average moons in the
inner we have 35 average moons
in the outer so let's let's say
we consider that anything you
know less than 10 or something
would be an outlier what we can
do is add having the average
number of moons greater than 10 so
this is the average of zero this
is 35 so what you would expect
is for the inner to disappear
we got rid of that entire group
if you think about students
and we have kind of three three
columns of students and one has
five members in the group and
one has 10 members in the group
and the other has one member
and if you're trying to work on
something you might say look okay the
group with one member let's just let's
just either get rid of you or move
you into another group that would
be like having the three groups and
saying having let's we're just going
to get rid of you in that case it
would be having count but these can
be having the min the max the average
for instance if i put average count
moons is greater than five i'm
kind of running blind here i'm not
exactly sure how many are inner and how
many are outer but let's take a
select location excuse me from planet
and we run this code and we have
one, two, three, four, five.
And one, two, three, we kind of have
a tie here. So if we did put this,
having the count, both of
them disappear because they
have five at each. But if we
say have greater than four,
which they do, both of them reappear.
So you can use count, min, max,
whichever aggregate function that
you decide to use that having clause.
All right, and let's conclude this
video with one last blue try it.
You can pause the video if
you want to try, and if you've
been following along, you
likely have the answer to this.
And the coding solution,
we changed it from location
to interest, select interest,
the average gravity,
as gravity average from
planet and group by interest
because we have an aggregate
and non-aggregate, And in
this case, having average
gravity is greater than 10.
All right, that's a stopping
point for now, but that gives
you an overview of select from
where group by having and also
how to comment out code. And
we will see you in video two.
Take care.